Guide to the Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. Papers 1808-1976 MS 438
New-York Historical Society
- Series VI. Print Matter, 1881-1959; 2.3 Linear feet in five record cartons
  - Subseries VI.A File Cabinet, 1884-1926; .7 Linear feet in two record cartons
    - Speeches—General, 1895-1926 (Box -, Folder -)
      - "The Position of Judaism", 1895 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Journal article from The North American, written by I. Zangwill.
      - Souvenir Program from Decennial Celebration of Witwatersrand Old Hebrew Congregation, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Congregation in Johannesburg.
      - The Jew as a Patriot, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Speech delivered by Joseph Herman Hertz, rabbi of the Witwatersrand Old Hebrew Congregation in Johannesburg, in honor of the decennial celebration of said congregation.
      - Issue of The Maccabaean Memorializing Theodore Herzl, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Has unidentified inscription.
      - Leopold Zunz—A Lecture, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 9)
        Delivered at the Jewish Theological Seminary by Louis Marshall.
      - Letter to Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. from Henry W. Scott, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1894-1901 (Box -, Folder -)
      - "Louis Kossuth: A Character Sketch," excerpted from Review of Reviews, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - The Two Great Commandments in Economics, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        By James E. Mills.
      - The Theory of Sociology, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        Written by Franklin H. Giddings, with inscription by Solomon Solis Cohen.
      - Speech by George F. Hoar to Senate on the Philippines, 1900 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Booklet of Speeches from Mass Meeting to Maintain the Independence of the Judiciary, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - The Ethical Record Journal, Vol. 2, 1901 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      - Excerpts from The North American Review, 1896 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        Includes article by Goldwin Smith, "Christianity's Millstone," with Maud Nathan's published response, "A Woman's View of Christianity's Millstone."
    - Miscellaneous, 1898-1922 (Box -, Folder -)
      - Clippings, 1908-1922 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        Includes an article on standard New York fire insurance policy written by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. and a copy of Pike's Peak Daily News with the names of people who summitted the peak on September 7, 1908, including Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. and his father.
      - Memo for a Judiciary Committee, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        Committee to renominate and reelect Justices Clarke and Greenbaum; Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. was a member of the general committee.
      - The Jews of Newport (Rhode Island), 1908 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Address delivered by Leon Hühner to the Old Jewish Synagogue in Newport, Rhode Island. Inscribed by the author.
      - The Problem of Jewish Charity in New York, 1911 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Address delivered by Morris D. Waldman, under the auspices of the Jewish Community (Kehillah) of New York City.
      - A Grain of Wheat, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        By A. Chodat, reprinted from The Popular Sciene Monthly.
      - The Trial of the Kaiser, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        By Edward Menkin, signed by the author.
      - War Memorials—Bulletin of the Municipal Art Society of New York City, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Unidentified inscription ("keep for E.J.N."). Contains pictures of war memorials across the United States, mainly in NYC.
      - Two Manifestos on Ireland, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        Includes Manifesto of Leaders of the Intellectual Life of Great Britain on Ireland and Report of the British Labor Commission to Ireland. Inscribed with date and initials by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.
      - Two Chapters from Evolution and Effort, 1898 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Contains chapters "Municipal Misgovernment" and "Summary and Conclusion" by Edmond Kelly.
      - List of Passengers on Special Train for American Bar Association's 31st Annual Meeting, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Inscribed with initials and his traincar information by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.
      - Feature from The Bankers Magazine on The American Exchange National Bank, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - A Declaration of Interdependence, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Book of resolutions and addresses in Westminster on the interdependence of England and the United States. Commemorates the first time July 4 was celebrated in England.
      - Memorial of Joseph Hodges Choate, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Written by William Archer Purrington and read before the New York County Lawyers' Association.
      - The Federal Prohibition Amendment, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Anti-prohibition amendment essay written by Otto Erickson and originally printed in Law Notes.
      - The World Wide Message of President Woodrow Wilson, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 13)
        Contains the address delivered by President Wilson in opening the Liberty Loan Campaign, with editorial comments by leading newspapers.
  - Subseries VI.B Loose Print Matter, 1881-1959; 1.6 Linear feet in four record cartons
    The materials in the subseries were originally interspersed randomly throughout the collection. They were gathered together into a series by the processing archivist and are now arranged in rough chronological order, with some interruption in the arrangement due to topical similarities or original order. The items are catalogued individually and divided into folders for convenience, rather than with intellectual intent.
    The subseries contains a wide variety of miscellaneous print matter, from a booklet on rent control and copies of Senate bills to records of Cardozo & Nathan cases and a book of poems written by Frances Nathan. The majority of the materials in the subseries are related to Judaism, especially Shearith Israel, though there are also many copies of memorials for friends of the family, as well as a fairly large quantity of print matter that directly references members of the Nathan family.
    - Brief and Abstract of Testimony for Supreme Court Case: William A. Stephens, Herman Blennerhassett, and Charter Oak Life Insurance Co. vs. Hoyt Sherman, assignee in bankruptcy of B.F. Allen, and B.F. Allen., 1881-1882 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      Holds printed brief and abstract, with an enclosed newspaper article about case. Inscribed with Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s signature.
    - Two Billings & Cardozo Cases, 1890-1892 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      Inscribed with Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s name, in stamp and script form. One report is also inscribed with, "With compliments from M.H.C." (Michael H. Cardozo).
    - Cardozo & Nathan Case: Albert J. Wheeler v. Aetna Insurance Co., circa 1905? (Box 10, Folder 16)
      Inscribed (likely by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr) to member of counsel for defendant.
    - Verses by Frances Nathan, 1928-1932 (Box 10, Folder 17)
      Inscribed with "ESN". Contains enclosed handwritten poems, perhaps in Frances's hand or perhaps simply copied.
    - Rand, McNally & Co's A Week at the Fair, 1892 (Box 10, Folder 18)
      Book on the Chicago World's Columbian Exposition, inscribed with Clarence Seixas Nathan's signature. A fold-out map of the fair, originally secured in the book, has fragmented and is loose in the folder.
    - "Jews in America" (Re-print from the Jewish Encyclopedia), 1901 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Views on the Synod, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      Compiled by Committee of the Central Conference of American Rabbis.
    - Jewish Ideals and the War, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      An address delivered by Lucien Wolf, Vice-President of the Jewish Historical Society of England.
    - Educational Reforms in Europe in Their Relation to Jewish Emancipation, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      Article by Max J. Kohler, originally printed in The Jewish Forum. Inscribed with Elvira Nathan Solis's initials.
    - The United States and German Jewish Persecutions, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      Article written by Max J. Kohler, originally published in "Bulletin of the Jewish Academy of Arts and Sciences," and inscribed by author with brief note to Elvira Nathan Solis.
    - Program for Service in Max J. Kohler's Memory, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - 3 Booklets on the 250th Anniversary of Jewish Settlement in America, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Service Program for Consecration of Shearith Israel's Mill Street Synagogue, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - The American Hebrew Feature Issue on Mill Street Consecration, 1897 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - A Message to Garcia, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      A little booklet about obedience by Elbert Hubbard.
    - The Unchanging Law: Shearith Israel's Heritage and Hope, 1916 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Sabbath sermon by D. de Sola Pool.
    - Pocket Guidebook to Military Insignia, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Inscribed with Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s initials.
    - Program for Dinner Honoring René Viviani, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      In French and English.
    - Two Copies of The American Hebrew, 1917 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Have inscriptions detailing the location of articles about Shearith Israel within the journals.
    - Booklet on Foreign Exchange, circa 1918? (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. Case: Nathan v. Hendricks, 1894 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Concerning the will of Charlotte Gomez.
    - Cardozo & Nathan Case: Prescott v. Ball, circa 1918? (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Ephraim Williams—A Soldier, 1918-1919 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Two copies of journal published by the Williams Club, featuring men in military service.
    - New York County Lawyers' Association Committee on Discipline Case, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Summary of the Organization and Operations of the American Expeditionary Force, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      As submitted to the Secretary of War by John J. Pershing. Includes list of wars/expeditions the U.S. has engaged in since its founding.
    - Columbia Law Review Vol. XVIII, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - New York State Senate Act on Partnerships, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Two Volumes of Williams Alumni Review, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - The West End Bulletin No. 13 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Federation for the Support of Jewish Philanthropic Societies of New York City Pamphlets, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - List of Invites to Economic Club of New York Meeting, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Book of Addresses at Reception for Cardinal Mercier, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - List of Members of Congress and Congressional Committees, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Petition to Review Order of Federal Trade Comission, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - The Traditional Code of Jewish Education, 1924 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Written by D. de Sola Pool and originally published in Jewish Education journal.
    - Three Memorial Booklets for Clarence Seixas Nathan, 1924 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - The Judeans—Constitution and List of Members, 1931 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Three Memorial Speeches, 1934-1935 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Two speeches by Rev. David de Sola Pool (one for Israel Unterberg, one for his wife Bella Unterberg) and one by Mordechai Kaplan, also for Israel Unterberg.
    - Report of the Committee on the Judiciary to the Bar, 1939 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Permanent Roll of Delegates to Republican National Convention, 1940 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Memorial Booklet for Sol M. Stroock, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Written by Joseph M. Proskauer and published by the Jewish Theological Seminary.
    - Albert Edward Henschel and His Connection with the Creation of the Greater New York, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      By Leon Huhner and inscribed by the author, originally printed by the American Jewish Historical Society.
    - Robert Moses on The Spreading City and New York City's Public Improvement Outlook, 1954 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - The Little Book on Rent Control, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Insanity, Suicide and Accident Insurance, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      By George I. Swetlow, inscribed by the author.
    - Henry Solomon Hendricks Memorial Booklets, 1959 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Includes Shearith Israel bulletin and American Jewish Historical Society pamphlet written by David de Sola Pool.
    - Gene Ryan's Songs "U" All Know Booklet, Undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Pre-Publication Booklet on Georges Lukomski's Old European Synagogues, Undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Fifty Years of Social Service: The History of the Jewish Social Service Association, 1926 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      Published when Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. was First Vice-President.
    - The Dutch and Quaker Colonies in America, Vol. 1, 1903 (Box 12, Volume 1)
      By John Fiske.
    - The Dutch and Quaker Colonies in America, Vol. 2, 1903 (Box 14, Volume 1)
    - Louis Marshall: Champion of Liberty, Vol. 1 and 2, 1957 (Box 14, Volume 2)
      Selected papers and addresses, edited by Charles Reznikoff. Books packaged together in a slipcase.
    - Clippings (3 folders of 6), 1929-1956 (Box 19, Folder 7-9)
      Folder 8 contains clippings on Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo and Dr. Solomon Solis-Cohen. Folder 9 contains clippings on President Eisenhower's election to the U.S. presidency.
    - Clippings (3 folders of 6), 1918-1958 (Box 19, Folder 15-17)
      Folders 6 and 7 contain WWI clippings.
    - Jewish Publications on Relatives (2 folders), 1927-1932 (Box 19, Folder 21-22)
      Copies of The Jewish Exponent, The Jewish Tribune, and American Hebrew that contain articles on Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo, Solomon Solis-Cohen, and Jacob Da Silva Solis Cohen.
- Series VII. Memorabilia, 1808-1966; 4.2 Linear feet in 3 record cartons, oversize folders and an oversize book slipcase
  The items in the series were originally scattered randomly throughout the collection, and were grouped together by the processing archivist. The series is now arranged in subject folders that advance in rough chronological order with the exception of object memorabilia, which is the first set of items in the series and is listed by individual object, and special cases in which interrelated subject folders are filed next to each other, thereby breaking the general sequence.
  The series contains a wide assortment of memorabilia, including mementos from Horace Mann, Collegiate, Williams, and Columbia, awards and certificates, photographs, Nathan family heirlooms (including pedigrees, letters, and marriage certificates), and souvenir programs from various events. Some of the memorabilia is related to other series in the collection, especially Series II and IV, or Manhattan Borough Presidency and Jewish Leadership.
  - Oversize Civil Defense Armband, circa 1940s (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
  - Large Embossed Slipcase, Undated (Box 13)
  - Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. for Manhattan Borough President Napkin, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Automobile and Building License for War Trade Board, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    In initials-embossed leather wallet.
  - Shirt Collar, circa 1960? (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Hair, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 5 Passports, 1955-1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Belonging to Mabel U. Nathan and Edgar J. Nathan, Jr., with enclosed vaccination records.
  - Postcards, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Contains Haynes Photo Yellowstone postcards and a postcard advertising Fourth Liberty bonds.
  - Assorted Stationery, 1918-1964 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Contains blank stationery with letterheads from offices Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. held.
  - Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s Misc. Writings, 1928-1963 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Contains memorial speeches and booklets written by Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. for various friends and relatives, as well as a few articles and speeches about other assorted topics.
  - Fifteenth Annual March of Dimes Fashion Show Program, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Print of Painting by Isabella Banks Markell, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Contains note by artist to Mabel.
  - Three Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletins, 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Bulletins feature light annotations by Mabel U. Nathan.
  - Typescript of Poem by Solomon Solis-Cohen, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Poem written in 1882.
  - Dennison's Napkin Label, Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Features a note from "ENS" to Emily, dated November 9.
  - New York and Cuba Mail Steamship Company Passenger Accommodation Plans, Undated (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Oversize document.
  - Assorted Photos, circa 1880?-1958 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Includes a photo of Albert Dreyfous, a couple of old photos of an unidentified woman (likely Edgar J. Nathan's wife, Mabel), a few unidentified group shots, and some political photos, including photos of Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. swearing people in and a shot of him and Arnold Zander. Also includes a photo of Williams Class of 1913 40th and 45th anniversaries.
  - Assorted Oversized Photos, circa 1940?-1961 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 1)
    Includes photos of Edgar J. Nathan shaking hands with various people including New York Secretary of State Thomas Curran, a headshot, and Supreme Court Justice dinners dated from 1952-1961.
  - Headshots (4 folders), Undated (Box 11, Folder 8-11)
    Folder 11 contains typed out names and addresses of Edgar J. Nathan's contacts.
  - Ketubah, 1808 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    Ketubah (marriage certificate) of Seixas Nathan and Sarah Mendes.
  - Gomez Family Genealogy, circa 1850s? (Box 11, Folder 13)
    Copy by Horatio Gomez of Sephardic Jewish Gomez family genealogy originally recorded by Issac Gomez. Envelope says "Albert Dreyfous".
  - Nathan Pedigree, circa 1900? (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Letter to Abraham Seixas from Issac Seixas, 1823 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Collage of Heritage Clippings, Undated (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Contains clippings from 1762-1849, some (or all) about Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s ancestors.
  - Clarence S. Nathan Scrapbook (Folder 1 of 2), 1879-1922 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Clarence S. Nathan Scrapbook (Folder 2 of 2), 1895 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Clarence S. Nathan's oversize 1895 passport certificate.
  - Father's Academic Mementos, 1876-1881 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    Booklets and papers from Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s time at Columbia University, as well as his high school thesis/"graduating essay."
  - Father's Dinner Programs, 1904-1913 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    Contains programs for Bnai Jeshurun dinner, NY State Bankers Association, dinner for Supreme Court Justice Hughes, and British Ambassador James Bryce.
  - Stock Certificates, 1897-1941 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    Includes stocks belonging to Samuel Derecktor, Carl M. Loeb and Co., Edgar J. Nathan, Jr., Edgar J. Nathan, Sr., Mabel Nathan, and Issac N. Solis, for companies Rossland and Deer Park Mining, Derwel Realty, Ford Mining and Milling, and Tareyton Realty.
  - Souvenir Programs from President McKinley Inauguration, 1901 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    One book has "E.N.S." inscribed in it.
  - Horace Mann Yearbook, 1909 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Mabel U. Nathan's high school yearbook, with signatures from classmates.
  - Collegiate Yearbooks (6 folders), 1906-1910 (Box 12, Folder 3-8)
    Contain pictures of Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. and Henry Solomon Hendricks in high school.
  - Williams Memorabilia, 1913 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Social Satire and Poems, 1915-1954 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    Contains satirical poems, scripts, and faux newspapers written for dinners, weddings, and other social events, which tease people including Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. and a number of his friends and relatives. Also contains two unidentified serious poems.
  - Wedding Materials (Folder 1 of 2), 1917 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    Contains various papers from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s marriage to Mabel Unterberg, including the guest list, dinner menu, Shearith Israel record, etc.
  - Wedding Materials (Folder 2 of 2), 1917 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
    Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. and Mabel Unterberg's ketubah.
  - Materials from 27th Division Homecoming, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Bar Association Event Programs, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    Materials from dinners honoring lawyers' services in WWI, including a song book.
  - Dinner Programs, 1921-1928 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    From: Reception of Marshal Ferdinand Foch by the American Legion, National Republican Club Annual Lincoln Dinner, flag service to commemorate the sesquicentennial of adoption of U.S. flag, NY County Lawyers' Association Annual Dinner.
  - Lindbergh Souvenirs and Correspondence, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    Photographs, telegrams, postcards, and dinner program re: Charles Lindbergh's non-stop flight from New York to Paris.
  - Mabel Nathan's Certificates, 1915-1950 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Mabel Nathan's NYU Woman's Law Class Certificate, 1915 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 3)
    Inscribed with Mabel U. Nathan's signature on the back.
  - Awards and Certificates (Folder 1 of 2), 1917-1963 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    Contains alumni awards/honorary degree dipolomas, as well as other small certificates.
  - Awards and Certificates (Folder 2 of 2), 1876-1957 (Box Oversize Small, Folder 3)
    Various oversized certificates. Includes Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s diploma from Friends Seminary, certificates naming Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. a lawyer, an employee of the War Trade Board, Manhattan Borough President, and New York Supreme Court Justice, as well as other significant awards and certificates, such as honorary degrees from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s alma maters.
  - Collegiate School Diploma, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Columbia Bicentennial Programs (Folder 1 of 2), 1954 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Columbia Bicentennial (Folder 2 of 2), 1954 (Box 19, Folder 23)
    Clippings.
  - Williams Honorary Degree (Folder 1 of 2), 1955 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    Contains various documents from ceremony, including ribbon, programs, invitations, tickets, and photographs (though not the actual degree).
  - Williams Honorary Degree (Folder 2 of 2), 1955 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Collegiate Alumni Award, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    Contains various documents related to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s Collegiate award, including articles, programs, etc. (though, again, not the actual award).
  - 11th Williams President Induction (Folder 1 of 2), 1961 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    Contains programs, nametags, invitations, and correspondence/articles about John Edward Sawyer's induction as president of Williams College.
  - 11th Williams President Induction (Folder 2 of 2), 1961 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Copies of Marriage, Death, and Birth Certificates, 1963-1965 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Memorial Publications and Speeches (4 folders), 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 33-36)
    Various booklets, programs, speeches, and clippings memorializing Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. Also contains his sons' correspondence related to the creation of these materials.